A Guide to the Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records, 1850-1928
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records, 1850-1928
Library of Virginia
12 volumes.
Pulaski County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled. please check alternative form available heading for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Pulaski County in 2008 under accession number 43684.
Alternative Form Available
Please see Pulaski County Microfilm index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.
Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers, 1850-1855 is available as microfilm Pulaski County (Va.) Reel 56
Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book, 1906-1928 is available as microfilm Pulaski County (Va.) Reel 56
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Business Records, both volumes and loose records are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safekeeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business records exhibit appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments. These records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
Locality History: Pulaski County was named for Casimir, the Polish patriot who served in the American army during the Revolutionary War and who was killed during the siege of Savannah in 1779. It was formed from Montgomery and Wythe Counties in 1839. Its area is 318 square miles, and the county seat is Pulaski.
Scope and Content
Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records, 1850-1928, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Pulaski County (Va.). Represented records largerly consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, minute books and account books.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers, 1850-1855
Series II: J. Farmer Physician Ledger, 1867-1898
Series III: Lee L. Summers and Company Daybooks and Ledgers, 1889-1896
Series IV: Fizer and Hall Ledgers, 1899-1907
Series V: Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book, 1906-1928
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also: Pulaski County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1905-035
See also: Pulaski County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1884-027
See also: Pulaski County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-006
Additional Pulaski County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers, 1850-1855, 3 volumes
  Historical Information: The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers, 1850-1855, were used by the railroad's engineering department to record the work performed by various contractors hired to perform grading and masonry work on specific sections of the railroad during its construction. Accounts were recorded for each contractor and include the contractor's name and the section and division of the railroad worked on. Each account entry includes a detailed list of the worked performed and the amounts paid for the service. Work performed by these railroad workers included earth excavation, rock excavation, and the building of culverts. Monthly Estimates Ledger, 1850-1852, contains a small account book that details the numbers of employees and equipment provided by the contractors. Accounts were kept for the number of overseers, mechanics, men, boys, hand carts, and teams used by each contractor. The number of workers who became sick during the construction was also noted. Monthly Estimates Ledger, 1853-1855, includes an article of agreement composed specifically for the work performed by contractors. The document provides a detailed description of the standards and quality expectations of the grading and masonry work.
  Also see: Pulaski County Chancery Cause, Pryde and Jones versus Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company. It can be found in the Local Records Collection at the Library of Virginia. The index number is 1859-006. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers 1850-1855
- J. Farmer Physician Ledger, 1867-1898, 1 volume
  Historical Information: J. Farmer Physician Ledger, records the accounts of individual patients. Entries are arranged in chronological order under the individual account name. Each entry includes the date, type of transaction, and the monies debited and credited. Each entry documents the name of the patient treated by listing self for the account holder, wife, child, or the patient's first name. Transactions include services rendered such as examinations, extraction of teeth, dressing wounds, and setting broken bones. Medicine purchases are also recorded and include such items as alcohol, castor oil, pills, cod liver oil, whiskey, iodine, pepsin, liniment, carbolic acid, and laudanum. There are also purchases for items not related to medicine -- corn, hay, lard, and butter. Also included in the ledger is a loose letter from J. B. Jordan dated 7 January 1883 and addressed to Dr. Farmer. Jordan, most probably James B. Jordan (born about 1850) another physician in nearby Newbern, Virginia, requests that Farmer visit a sick patient while he is away attending to an obstetrical case.
  Also see: Pulaski County Chancery Cause, Jerry Farmer versus Heirs of Elbert S. Trinkle. It can be found in the Local Records Collection at the Library of Virginia. The index number is 1884-027. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - J. Farmer Physician Ledger 1867-1898
- Lee L. Summers and Company Daybooks and Ledgers, 1889-1896, 4 volumes
  Historical Information: Lee L. Summers and Company records consist of two daybooks and two ledgers. Daybooks, 1889-1890 and 1892-1893, record transactions on a daily basis as they occurred. Information found in each entry includes date, customer name, merchandise purchased, and monies debited and credited. Items purchased include hay, straw, meal, chop, and oats. Account information was transferred to the corresponding ledgers and listed under the customer's name. Employee accounts were often recorded in the daybooks and note the wages paid for tasks such as hauling hay. Also recorded in the Daybook are entries for the company's incidental expenses such as postage and the costs of sending telegrams. Ledgers, 1889-1891 and 1891-1896, record the accounts of individual customers. Entries are organized in chronological order under the individual account name. Each entry includes the date the transaction occurred, items purchased, and monies debited and credited. Also included in the ledgers are lists of bills receivable and a record of deposits and withdrawals from the Pulaski National Bank.
  Also see: Pulaski County Chancery Cause, L. L. Summers versus James Gemmell and others. It can be found in the Local Records Collection at the Library of Virginia. The index number is 1905-035. Available Digitally through the Chancery Records Index.
  - Lee L. Summers and Company Daybooks and Ledgers 1889-1896
- Fizer and Hall Ledgers, 1899-1907, 3 volumes
  Historical Information: Fizer and Hall Ledgers, 1899-1904, 1901-1905, and 1902-1907, record the accounts of individual customers at the butcher shop. Each account lists transactions in chronological order as they occurred. Entries document date, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, and monies debited and credited to the accounts. Items purchased include various types and cuts of meat such as beef, pork, chicken, turkey, sausage, veal, mutton, bacon, and oysters. Other items sold include butter, lard, potatoes, cabbage, beans, onions, and eggs. Ledger, 1899-1904, also includes several loose papers dated 1905 and 1906. Most of these are James K. Polk Fizer's account receipts with area merchants for clothing and advertising. There are also several freight bills for Fizer and Hall. In addition, there is a letter addressed to James K. Polk Fizer, 27 August 1906, written by his aunt and uncle, M. N. and C. O. Carper, who were living in Greenwood, Indiana. The letter seeks advice on how to divide land inherited after the death of a distant relative, Virginia Carper Wright.
  - Fizer and Hall Ledgers 1899-1907
- Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book, 1906-1928>, 1 volume
  Historical Information: The Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book, 1906-1928, records the meetings of the company's board of directors and stockholders. Early meetings, beginning in December 1906, concern the formation of the company and include such business as the election of officers and board members, drafting by-laws, hiring employees, fixing salary rates, selling stock, and raising money to construct the storage plant. The majority of meetings concern the state of the company, the election of officers, the selling of stock, and the hiring of employees. Annual statements were provided at meetings of the stockholders. These statements documented the resources (real estate, machinery, bills receivable, cash) and liabilities of the company. Reports of receipts (stock sold, storage fees) and disbursements (rent, labor, fuel) were also provided. The final meeting of the stockholders, 29 February 1928, details the sell-out of the company to the Jervian Corporation.
  - The Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book 1906-1928